<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dr. Burnet's sermon before His Highness the Prince of Orange, at the Cathedral of Exon, on reading his declaration</title>
            <author>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77909</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5870C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42711</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875630</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875630</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152235</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77909)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152235)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2286:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dr. Burnet's sermon before His Highness the Prince of Orange, at the Cathedral of Exon, on reading his declaration</title>
                  <author>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[Pr]inted for W. C[o]ldh[a]m,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.LXXXIX [1689]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errors in paging: p. 5-8 numbered 9-12 repectively.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, print show-through and broken type; bracketed material in imprint supplied from WIng (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]-C².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Lambeth Palace Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 2nd, I, 14 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Religious aspects --  Christianity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152235:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Dr. Burnet's SERMON, BEFORE <hi>His Highneſs</hi> THE PRINCE OF ORANGE. At the Cathedral of <hi>Exon,</hi> on Reading His DECLARATION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>ted for <hi>W. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> MDCLXXXLX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:152235:2"/>
            <head>THE Divine Authority OF KINGS ASSERTED.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>2 SAM. 1.14.</bibl>
                  <p>And <hi>David</hi> ſaid unto him, How waſt thou not afraid to stretch forth thine hand to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Lord's Anointed?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>BEfore we enter upon the conſideration of this place of Scripture, we muſt come fairly to it by making our way through the <hi>Context,</hi> to which the <hi>Text</hi> doth relate; and thus it was. There had been now a War between <hi>Saul</hi> and the <hi>Philiſtines;</hi> a War that was ſounded on the Law of God, whereby the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were forbidden to <hi>make any Covenant with the Inhabitants of</hi> Canaan, <hi>or to ſhew them mercy, Deut.</hi> 7.2. This War ended in the <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>Saul;</hi> and the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of his People though he was made King by God's <hi>own</hi> appointment, though he was God's <hi>own</hi> Vice-gerent over God's <hi>own</hi> inheritance, and undertook a quarrel purſuan to God's <hi>own</hi> Will, yet in the Concluſion both He and his Forces (Good <hi>Jonathan</hi> himſelf not excepted) are routed upon Mount <hi>Gilboa</hi> by the <hi>Uncircumciſed Philiſtines:</hi> To ſhew that <hi>Succeſs</hi> in War is not an Argument of the Righteouſneſs of a <hi>Cauſe,</hi> or of the Righteouſneſs of a <hi>Party,</hi> but of the unſearchable Wiſdom and Righteouſneſs of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul</hi> being defeated was full of Horror and Deſperation, and reſolved to haſten out of the <hi>World,</hi> ſince he had fled before the <hi>Philiſtines;</hi> and becauſe his Armour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer could not be entreated (by reaſon of that <hi>Awful</hi> regard he bore to <hi>Majeſty</hi>) to befriend his undone <hi>Soveraign</hi> with a Mortal Blow, <hi>Saul</hi> gives <hi>himſelf</hi> his Deaths-wound with his own hands.</p>
            <p>An <hi>Amalekite</hi> happening to be there, took off his Royal Diadem and Bracelet, and with great Speed carryed them to <hi>Ziklag</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> who by Common Fame was known to have been Anointed next Heir to the Crown of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> received the news of <hi>Saul</hi>'s and <hi>Jonathan</hi>'s Death, with exceſs of <hi>Sorrow:</hi> But hearing that this <hi>Amalekite</hi> had had an hand in <hi>Saul</hi>'s deſtruction, his Heart was ſtruck through with <hi>Amazement and Indignation.</hi> Though <hi>Saul</hi> had been his Blood-thirſty <hi>Enemy,</hi> yet his Soul was on a Flame, at the ſad Tidings of his being <hi>Murdered,</hi> and though this young man was not one of <hi>Saul</hi>'s Subjects, but a Stranger; yet for the Sake of God, whoſe Impreſs the Unfortunate King bore, for the Honor of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rſty,</hi> and out of reſpect to <hi>Saul</hi>'s Divine <hi>Unction</hi> and <hi>Character,</hi> he was reſolved to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152235:2"/>revenge the Kings death, with every drop of this <hi>Amalekites</hi> Blood; and this was the Preamble to his juſt Sentence, <hi>How waſt thou not affraid to ſtretch forth thine Hand to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Lord's Anointed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words we are to conſider, by way of Explication:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, the matter of Fact, which this <hi>Amalekite</hi> own'd himſelf to have been guilty of.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Davids</hi> deep <hi>Reſentment</hi> of the Relation which this <hi>Amalekite</hi> made of the matter.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The matter of Fact was, that he had ſtretched out his hand to deſtroy the King of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> this he acknowledged, and ſeemed to boaſt of, as a Meritorious Office, which he had done for <hi>David,</hi> who was to be <hi>Saul</hi>'s Succeſſor in the Throne. Now it has been a great doubt both among <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> whether this was a <hi>Reality,</hi> or only a <hi>Pretence.</hi> Many of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Doctors affirm (which is alſo the general ſenſe of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Writers) that <hi>Saul</hi> killed himſelf, and that the <hi>Amalekite</hi> was a <hi>Liar</hi> as to that particular. Nor doth this opinion want its Reaſons. For in the laſt Chapter of the Firſt Book of <hi>Samuel</hi> (where the manner of <hi>Sauls</hi> Death is related) no mention is made of the <hi>Amalekite,</hi> but the Text ſaith, that <hi>Soul took a Sword and fell upon it,</hi> v. 4. On the other ſide, <hi>Joſephus,</hi> and ſome more tells us, that <hi>Saul</hi> had not the <hi>Only</hi> hand in the caſe, but that the <hi>Amalekile</hi> was the <hi>Principal</hi> actor.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antiquit. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daic. lib.</hi> 6.</note> Nor doth this opinion want its Reaſons neither. For the <hi>Amalekites</hi> were as much Enemies to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> were; and this <hi>Amale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kite</hi> was on Mount <hi>Gilboa</hi> when <hi>Saul</hi> fell; and he did not only poſt away to <hi>David</hi> as a Meſſenger of the Fact, but perſiſted in the ſtory as an <hi>Agent</hi> that had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it; <hi>perſiſted</hi> to the end too, without <hi>owning</hi> his Folly, or <hi>excuſing</hi> his Lye (which probably he would have done) when he ſaw, that a Sentence of Death a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelf was the <hi>Only</hi> welcom and reward, that he was to receive.</p>
            <p>Now for the Solution of this doubt, there ſeem to be ſome grounds for a <hi>Third</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion yet, which will make the whole ſtory to <hi>Agree, viz.</hi> that <hi>Saul</hi> and this <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lekite</hi> did (both of them) jointly <hi>Concurr</hi> in the carrying of this ſad Tragedy on. For that <hi>Saul</hi> fell upon his Sword, and ſo gave himſelf his Deaths-wound, is clear. That his Armour-bearer might look upon him as Dead (though indeed he was not) may be <hi>Probable.</hi> That being incumbered with his Arms and Coat of Mail, he did not diſpatch himſelf <hi>Fully,</hi> is not incredible: And then 'tis likely enough, both that <hi>Saul</hi> did beg a Bloody Kindneſs of the <hi>Amalekite,</hi> for fear of falling alive into the hands of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and that this <hi>Amalekite</hi> did readily gratify him, in hopes of a Richer booty, than the price of the Crown and the Bracelet came to.</p>
            <p>But it is not much material, whether this <hi>Amalekite</hi> was <hi>Really</hi> Guilty, or had a mind only to <hi>Father</hi> the action. We will now (as <hi>David</hi> did) take his own Word for it, and <hi>Suppoſe</hi> him to have ſpoken Truth. For none can be better believed, then he that confeſſeth againſt <hi>Himſelf.</hi> Every man will be ſure to make the beſt of his <hi>own</hi> ſtory; and though an Evidence may Swear away <hi>other</hi> mens Lives, he will be tender of his <hi>own,</hi> and beware of being his own <hi>Accuſer,</hi> though he depoſeth to a <hi>Lye.</hi> We will not therefore contraſt the Credit of his own Teſtimony, but acquieſce in what he ſaid. and look upon him as a Criminal; and proceed to.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:152235:3"/>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing (which is moſt pertinent to our buſineſs) <hi>Davids</hi> deep <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment</hi> of this <hi>Amalekites</hi> relation; it was a <hi>Dreadful</hi> ſtory, a moſt <hi>Horrible</hi> and <hi>Fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> thing in the account of this good man, <hi>How waſt thou not affraid to ſtretch forth thine hand to deſtroy the Lord's Anointed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He had it not been a Sin of a moſt <hi>Horrid</hi> nature and a <hi>clamorous</hi> voice, he who was ſo <hi>near</hi> the Throne, would at leaſt have <hi>forgiven</hi> the man, that did ſo readily help him to the actual <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> of it, eſpecially being an Heir that had waited with ſo much Suffering, and been provoked by <hi>Saul</hi> with ſo many Indignities. But <hi>King-Killing</hi> is a Crime that is Odious and Abominable in the eyes even of thoſe, that fare well by the <hi>Regicide.</hi> To which purpoſe the Learned <hi>Crot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi> has right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerved out of one of the <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtories,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tacit. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 1.</note> that when the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror <hi>Galba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was Murdered, <hi>Vitellius,</hi> though (Humanly ſpeaking) he had reaſon enough to be glad of the Fact, having thereby got the power in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his hands, yet out of a due ſenſe he had of the <hi>Horridneſs</hi> of the villany he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thoſe Traitors, who had ſerved his <hi>turn,</hi> to be ſlain all of them, when they had the confidence to Addreſs for a Reward.</p>
            <p>An inſtanc not much unlike King <hi>David</hi>'s dealing with this <hi>Amalekite,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n he brought <hi>Saul</hi>'s Blood upon his <hi>own</hi> head; becauſe he had ſtretched forth his hand to deſtroy the Lord's Anointed.</p>
            <p>Thoſe words, <hi>the Lord's Ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nted,</hi> denote the <hi>great,</hi> nay the <hi>Sole</hi> thing, which we find here, and in other places to have made ſuch a <hi>deep</hi> and <hi>continual</hi> Impreſſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>David</hi>'s Spirit: So that when he had cut off the skirt of <hi>Saul</hi>'s robe, his Heart <hi>Smote</hi> him: When he was tempted to Kill him in the Cave, he <hi>abhorr'd</hi> the very thoughts of it; when <hi>Abiſhai</hi> would have deſtroyed him at one blow as he was aſleep, <hi>David with held</hi> him with a ſtrong hand: When <hi>Abner</hi> was ſo careleſs of his Maſters ſafety, as to let him fall into <hi>David</hi>'s power, <hi>David reprehended</hi> him: And at laſt, when this <hi>Amalekite</hi> had ſmote him (him, who had ſo long <hi>hunted</hi> after <hi>David</hi>'s Soul) He preſently <hi>ſmote</hi> the <hi>Amalekite;</hi> all this was grounded upon this <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Weighty</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, that <hi>Saul</hi> was the <hi>Lord's Anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A King is ſaid to be the <hi>Lord's Anointed</hi> in a Two-fold reſpect.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In reſpect of that <hi>outward, Ceremonial</hi> Unction, whereby for <hi>Sate-ſake</hi> he is by the Prieſt ſeparated from the People, or rather <hi>Declared, Notified, and Acknowledged</hi> to be a <hi>Sacred</hi> perſon. Now this is not the great thing conſiderable, becauſe it is but a <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te</hi> and <hi>Form</hi> that is not abſolutely <hi>neceſſary:</hi> For many Princes at this day are not <hi>thus</hi> Anointed at all; I know not whether this Unction was <hi>ever</hi> uſed to Pagan Kings, who yet were Gods Miniſters, and had Gods Authority, as well as others; it was a long time before it came to be uſed even in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World; <hi>anciently</hi> and <hi>originally</hi> it was a rite peculiar to the <hi>Jews</hi> alone; and among <hi>them</hi> it was not u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>conſtantly</hi> neither; but when the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> was <hi>broken,</hi> or a diſpute aroſe about a Succeſſors <hi>Title;</hi> commonly <hi>one</hi> of a Family was <hi>Anointed</hi> for all his <hi>Poſterity</hi> and <hi>Iſſue;</hi> and even <hi>then</hi> the man was not made King becauſe he was <hi>Anointed,</hi> but he was <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed</hi> becauſe he was <hi>King.</hi> Though there be neither <hi>Horn,</hi> nor <hi>Cruſe</hi> of Oyl in the caſe, yet be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> nearer the leſs, and that upon an <hi>Higher,</hi> and more <hi>Noble</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:152235:3"/>
            <p n="2">2. In reſpect of that <hi>inward</hi> and <hi>eſſential</hi> Unction, which he receives at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry firſt <hi>minute</hi> of his Kingſhip, and by which he is Sanctified and ſet <hi>apart</hi> and <hi>above</hi> all others in that very Article of time, and which from that day forward is <hi>inſeparable</hi> from his Perſon. Now this Unction conſiſteth in that Supreme <hi>Power</hi> which is given unto him, in that Sacred <hi>Authority</hi> which is veſted in him, in that inviolable <hi>Majeſty</hi> which is inſeparable from him, in that Divine <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Impreſs</hi> whereby he bears a <hi>different</hi> and <hi>ſingular</hi> Character, and becomes <hi>Hallowed.</hi> And becauſe he receives all this at the hands of <hi>God</hi> alone, becauſe he oweth all this, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Prieſt</hi> nor <hi>People,</hi> but to <hi>God</hi> alone; becauſe this <hi>Power, Authority, Majeſty, Image,</hi> and <hi>Character</hi> is given him by the <hi>Lord</hi> only, therefore, he is called, <hi>The Lord's Anointed,</hi> that is, a Perſon made ſo Sacred by <hi>God</hi> by the Communication of his <hi>own</hi> Authority, that now he cannot be treated with rudeneſs or violence, without Diſhonoring <hi>God's</hi> own Majeſty, and ſtriking at the Face of God <hi>himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this purpoſe we are to obſerve, what God ſaid of King <hi>Cyrus,</hi> an <hi>Heathen,</hi> an <hi>Infidel,</hi> a <hi>Foreigner,</hi> no more related unto him than a <hi>Philistine,</hi> or an <hi>Amale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kite</hi> Prince, yet all this notwithſtanding he calls him his <hi>Anointed,</hi> Iſ. 45. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord to his Anointed, to</hi> Cyrus, <hi>whoſe right hand I have holden</hi> (or ſtrengthened with Power) <hi>v.</hi> 1. — <hi>I have even called thee by thy name; I have ſurnamed thee, though thou haſt not known me,</hi> v. 4.</p>
            <p>This was <hi>Prophetically</hi> ſpoken, for at this time <hi>Cyrus</hi> was not ſo much as <hi>Born:</hi> And when he came to be King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> he was no more Anointed there, than <hi>Nero</hi> was at <hi>Rome;</hi> and yet, as the <hi>Prophet</hi> calls the former <hi>God's Anointed,</hi> ſo the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> calls the latter the <hi>Miniſter of God,</hi> the <hi>Ordained of God;</hi> and both <hi>Iſaiah</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake ſo upon theſe grounds, becauſe all Lawful Princes are endued with <hi>God's</hi> Power and Authority, whereof the <hi>Material</hi> and <hi>Ceremonial</hi> Unction among the <hi>Jews,</hi> was a <hi>Signification</hi> and <hi>Argument</hi> only.</p>
            <p>Now do but <hi>compare</hi> all this, with what is recorded of <hi>Saul,</hi> whom <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of in my Text, and ſtyles him, <hi>The Lord's Anointed.</hi> Not very long after he came to the Crown, out of Timorouſneſs and Infidelity, he-offered up Sacrifice <hi>himſelf</hi> in <hi>Samuels</hi> abſence, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. and therein he was an <hi>Uſurper</hi> of the <hi>Prieſtly</hi> Office. Afterwards, he ſpared the King of <hi>Amalek, c.</hi> 15. and the beſt of the ſpoil, contrary to what he was required to do, and therein he was a <hi>Rebel</hi> againſt Gods Commands. After this, he ſought the Life of <hi>David, c.</hi> 18. (the beſt Subject that ever any Prince had) and would have ſtruck him to the wall with a Javelin, and all this for <hi>David's</hi> good Service, therein he was a <hi>Tyrant:</hi> After this, he unjuſtly Kills at once 85. of the <hi>Lord's</hi> Prieſts, <hi>c.</hi> 22. beſides the Men and Women, Children, and Sucklings that were in <hi>Nob,</hi> and therein he was a <hi>Murderer.</hi> After this, he forſaketh the <hi>Lord</hi> for the <hi>Devil,</hi> and conſulteth a <hi>Witch</hi> at <hi>Ender, c.</hi> 28. and therein he was an <hi>Apostate.</hi> And after all this, laſt of all, as if he could not periſh by any impurer hands than his own, he ruſheth on the point of his Sword, <hi>c.</hi> 31. endeavours and attempts his own final Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and there he was a <hi>ſelf-Hemicide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all theſe Sins, he was the <hi>Lord's Ancinted</hi> ſtill; and <hi>David own'd, treated, reveer'd,</hi> and in the end <hi>vindicated</hi> him, as the <hi>Lord's Anointed.</hi> He diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152235:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:152235:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:152235:5"/>between the <hi>Sinner,</hi> and the <hi>Prince;</hi> He lookt upon his Perſonal <hi>Crimes</hi> with one eye, and upon his Holy <hi>Unction</hi> with another. And if the Scripture may be allowed to bear us out in <hi>any</hi> concluſion, we have warrant enough to infer hence, that the worſt of Kings (ſuppoſing him to be a Lawful King) hath a <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Indelible</hi> Character, for the ſake whereof, he ought to be accounted and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured as the <hi>Lord's Anointed,</hi> and conſequently as a <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Dread</hi> Soveraign.</p>
            <p>Nor will it avail us to conſider, <hi>how</hi> or by what <hi>means</hi> he came to his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, whether by <hi>Inheritance,</hi> or <hi>otherwiſe.</hi> A Lawful Prince is the Lord's A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed ever, beholding to God alone for his Power and Authority. <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> or <hi>Election</hi> may be the <hi>Inſtrument</hi> to <hi>convey</hi> the Title, but the <hi>Deed is Gods,</hi> and the Soveraign Power is a Donative and Eſtate which the King holdeth <hi>in Fee</hi> of God, and of God <hi>alone,</hi> whether it be by <hi>Nature,</hi> that the Man is brought forth; or whether it be by the <hi>Sword,</hi> that he cuts his way; or whether it be by the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> of Men, that he is pitcht upon, ſtill theſe are but the <hi>means,</hi> the <hi>ways,</hi> and the <hi>methods</hi> of a Nation, whereby a Prince is brought <hi>to</hi> the Throne: 'Tis God that gives him his Commiſſion to Reign <hi>in</hi> it; the Right of Governing, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority he hath over his People, the Power of Life and Death, the Crown and Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Regalities and Prerogatives of a King (however he may diminiſh or give ſome of them away) they are owing only to the Courteſie of <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this caſe 'tis neceſſary for us to diſtinguiſh between the <hi>Power</hi> it ſelf, and the <hi>Choice,</hi> or <hi>Application</hi> of the <hi>Perſon</hi> to that <hi>Power.</hi> Now, the <hi>Power</hi> is <hi>God's, by whom Kings Reign:</hi> But <hi>under</hi> God there may be divers <hi>Subordinate, Inſtrumental,</hi> and <hi>Ministerial</hi> hands to give a man a Right to that Power. Anciently and firſt of all, Monarchical Soveraignty went by <hi>Lineal Deſcent,</hi> and <hi>Proximity of Blood;</hi> and this was the <hi>Regal</hi> and <hi>beſt</hi> way. But in after Ages the Wickedneſs of a few Nations altered this courſe, and Monarchies came to be <hi>Elective.</hi> And though a Prince be <hi>choſen</hi> by the Suffrages of the People, yet this is but a <hi>Qualification</hi> of him to <hi>uſe</hi> that Power, and to <hi>exerciſe</hi> that Authority which is given by the <hi>King of Kings.</hi> Nay, though they <hi>Anoint</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> him, yet in all this they are the <hi>only</hi> Maſters of the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> to <hi>declare</hi> their Obligations to Obey, and to <hi>Aſſiſt</hi> in the Princes <hi>Inveſtitures;</hi> ſtill the <hi>Authority</hi> whereby he acteth, the <hi>Subſtantial</hi> and <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential</hi> Unction, is from above. They may put on his <hi>Robes,</hi> and gird him with the <hi>Sword,</hi> and place him in his Imperial <hi>Chair,</hi> and cover his Head with a Royal <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem;</hi> but when he is in his Throne, 'tis by a Superior Authority that he <hi>ſtrikes</hi> with his Sword, and by a Divine Commiſſion that he <hi>Commandeth, Governeth,</hi> and Miniſtreth Juſtice unto the People which he is ſet over: And ſo <hi>Valentinian</hi> told his Soldiers when they had choſen him Emperor, and asked him ſomething which he did not like; <hi>It was in your Power to chuſe me to rule over you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but ſince you have choſen me, what you deſire dependeth not upon your pleaſure, but mine. Your buſineſs is as my Subjects, to obey me; and my buſineſs is, as your Prince, to order what you are to do.</hi> Though <hi>Valentinian</hi> was taken from among the <hi>Soldiery,</hi> yet his <hi>Power</hi> was not derived from the <hi>Camp,</hi> but it was from <hi>God,</hi> as King <hi>Saul's</hi> was, when he was fetcht from among the <hi>Stuff,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>Things are beſt underſtood when they are Illuſtrated by familiar Inſtances.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152235:5"/>Take then 1. an Inſtance in an <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> matter: <hi>Judas</hi> the Traitor being dead, the Eleven think of Subſtituting ſome other in his Room, and by lot they Elected <hi>Matthias,</hi> Acts 1. But <hi>Matthias</hi> was not <hi>their</hi> Delegate, nor did he Act by <hi>their</hi> Commiſſion, or in <hi>their</hi> Name, or by <hi>their</hi> Power; but his Authority was from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as the reſt of the <hi>Apostles</hi> was: They indeed pitcht upon the <hi>Man,</hi> but his <hi>Apoſtleſhip,</hi> his Miniſterial <hi>Character,</hi> his power to Preach, to Adminiſter Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, to Bind and Looſe, this Power was from <hi>Heaven.</hi> 2. Take a ſecond Inſtance in an <hi>Oeconomical</hi> matter: Say a <hi>Servant</hi> chuſeth his <hi>Maſter,</hi> or a <hi>Wife</hi> her <hi>Husband,</hi> each of theſe pitch upon the <hi>Man,</hi> but neither of them gives him his <hi>Authority,</hi> but both conſent to <hi>ſubmit</hi> unto it; his power of Governing his whole Houſe-hold is from <hi>Nature.</hi> 3. Take a third Inſtance yet in a <hi>Political</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: Say a Pariſh do chuſe their <hi>Conſtable,</hi> or a City their <hi>Mayor,</hi> or a County their <hi>Sheriff;</hi> theſe indeed determine upon the <hi>Perſon,</hi> but they give them not their <hi>Power,</hi> nor do they act in the Names of their <hi>Electors;</hi> but their Authority to keep the Peace, to Diſtrain Goods, to Sieze and Execute Malefactors, is from the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>Kings</hi> Officers they are. Why, much like hereunto is that other Inſtance when a People chuſe their King (though it would be better for the World, if no People did ſo, <hi>Haereditary</hi> Government being the beſt:) After a great deal of Clamour, Diſorder, Animoſity, Strife, Confuſion, Diſtraction, and perhaps <hi>Bloodſhed,</hi> at laſt <hi>Neceſſity</hi> brings them to agree upon the <hi>Man:</hi> But the Kings Authority comes not from the dirty hands of a Rout, nor doth he act in the name of a Soveraign multitde, but his Power is from God: <hi>By his Command Kings are conſtituted, by whoſe pleaſure Men are born; God appoints them, and fits them according to the condition of the Times,</hi> ſaith <hi>Irenaeus, Iren. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>adv. Haereſ. cap.</hi> 24. And ſo <hi>Tertullian</hi> affirms, that <hi>the Emperor is thence, whence the man was before he was Emperor:</hi> Tertul. <hi>Apol. c.</hi> 30. <hi>He receivenh his Power from the ſame hand which gave him his Spirit.</hi> And elſewhere ſaith he, <hi>We (Christians) worſhip the Emperor ſo as 'tis lawful for us, and expedient for himſelf, as a Man next unto God; as one that hath received all that he hath from God; and as one that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior to God alone.</hi> Tertul. <hi>adv. Scapul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, if the caſe be thus, where a Monarchy is <hi>Elective</hi> (as the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire was, whatever is ſuggeſted to the <hi>contrary</hi>) the Plea is much the <hi>ſtronger</hi> for the Divine Authority of a Prince, where the <hi>Crown</hi> deſcendeth by <hi>Inheritance</hi> (as, God be bleſſed it doth with <hi>us,</hi> and for the good of the Kingdom, may it deſcend ſtill in that <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Peaceful</hi> courſe to the Worlds end) In this caſe, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the People is neither <hi>Eſſential</hi> nor <hi>Acceſſory;</hi> as they are not capable of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the Authority, ſo they are praecluded the liberty of diſputing about the Perſon (where there is an apparent or undoubted Heir) for <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> have alread <hi>determin'd</hi> the Controverſie. Men may <hi>Recognize</hi> his Right, (and in point of Conſcience are bound to do ſo) as the Men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did <hi>Recognize Saul's</hi> Right, <hi>after</hi> he had been <hi>Anointed;</hi> but where a Kingdom is <hi>Hereditary,</hi> ones Right taketh place upon the voidance of anothers <hi>Poſſeſſion;</hi> which is the ground of that Maxim in our Law (which is the ſharpeſt Dagger in the <hi>Republicans Heart</hi>) <hi>that the King cannot dye.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152235:6"/>
            <p>I have been the longer upon clearing the account of the Divine Authority of <hi>Kings,</hi> becauſe it was the <hi>only</hi> conſideration which <hi>David</hi> had in his thoughts, when he was moved to proceed ſo ſeverely againſt this <hi>Amalekite,</hi> for offering violence unto <hi>Saul. Quare non Timuisti?</hi> How came it about that thou waſt not <hi>afraid,</hi> that thy Heart did not ſink, that thy Soul could ſuffer thee to ſtretch forth thine hand to deſtroy the <hi>Lord's Anointed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And hence we may fairly proceed to Two Concluſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it is a <hi>Fearful</hi> thing, even to <hi>Reſist</hi> the Lords Anointed. A Fearful thing indeed (according to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Divinity) if it be a <hi>Fearful</hi> thing to be <hi>Damned.</hi> For <hi>Oppoſition</hi> tendeth to <hi>Deſtrustion;</hi> and there is no more difference between <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting</hi> and <hi>Killing,</hi> then there is between the <hi>means</hi> and the <hi>end,</hi> or between putting a Sword to a Princes <hi>Throat,</hi> and direct <hi>Cutting</hi> it. If he be a Murderer (by <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation</hi>) who hateth his <hi>Brother,</hi> he muſt be a Regicide (in the intent,) <hi>who draweth out his Artillery againſt his Prince, and Rebbels are beholding to our Charity alone, in this as well as other caſes, if we do not ſay, that never any ſubjects drew the ſword a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their King, but with a Reſolution (if there was no other Remedy) to ſheath it in his Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not intend (for the Time will not give me leave) to handle the caſe of a a <hi>Defenſive</hi> War againſt a Rightful Soveraign, (a caſe, that never was maintain- but by <hi>Republican Atheiſts.</hi>) When our Saviour commanded us, <hi>Not to reſiſt evil, Matth.</hi> 5.39. we muſt ſuppoſe him to teach us to ſuffer Indignities with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, as well from the hands of a Superior, as from the hands of an Equal. And when St. <hi>Paul</hi> affirms, that <hi>whoſoever reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God, Rom.</hi> 13.2. we muſt conclude, that a War againſt Lawful <hi>Authority</hi> is a War againſt <hi>Heaven.</hi> And when St. <hi>Peter</hi> requiring us to <hi>Honour the King,</hi> preſently Subjoined, <hi>Servants be ſubject to your Maſters with all fear, not only to the Good and Gentle, but alſo to the Froward,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18. we muſt look upon him to have taught us the neceſſity of <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> in the State, as well as at Home; for otherwiſe it would follow (what is <hi>unreaſonable</hi> to conceive) that <hi>Princes</hi> have not ſo <hi>much</hi> benefit by the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> for the ſecuring of <hi>their</hi> Authority, as every <hi>Ordinary</hi> and <hi>Private</hi> Man hath.</p>
            <p>And in ſaying thus much, God is my Witneſs that I aim at no other end, but to vindicate the <hi>Doctrine of the Croſs,</hi> which divers lately have endeavoured to expoſe to <hi>Contempt</hi> and <hi>Deriſion.</hi> But (to return to <hi>David</hi>'s practice in refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to <hi>Saul</hi>) becauſe <hi>David</hi>'s having of an <hi>Army,</hi> has been pleaded by <hi>Rebels</hi> to <hi>juſtifie Reſiſtance,</hi> for the removing of this Objection, many things are to be conſider'd. 1. That <hi>David</hi>'s caſe was <hi>particular;</hi> for he was already Anointed unto the Kingdom, and was <hi>Haeres Viventis,</hi> not only Lawful Heir, but as ſure of the Crown as if <hi>Saul</hi> had been dead. 2. That the little Army which <hi>David</hi> had, was not of his own <hi>Raiſing,</hi> but they <hi>reſorted</hi> unto him of their own accord; partly for <hi>Refuge-ſake</hi> (for they were <hi>Indigent</hi> and <hi>Diſconted</hi> Perſons) partly to ſhew <hi>David</hi> their beſt <hi>reſpects;</hi> partly out of <hi>pity</hi> and <hi>compaſſion</hi> to a wronged Prince, and the Hearts of Men are generally pitiful and compaſſionate in <hi>ſuch</hi> a caſe) and partly to <hi>endear</hi> themſelves to <hi>David,</hi> and to make their Fortunes by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152235:6"/>him when he ſhould come to the Crown. 3. That when the Men were come, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> uſed them rather as a Friendly <hi>Retinue,</hi> than as a formidable Army, to ſecure his own Life from the hands of <hi>Pick-thanks,</hi> who otherwiſe might be ready to ſhed his Blood to curry favour with <hi>Saul,</hi> and without <hi>Saul</hi>'s Order and Commiſſion. 4. That when <hi>David</hi> imployed his Retinue to <hi>Military</hi> purpoſes and after a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary</hi> manner, it was againſt thoſe People who were Enemies to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and who by the Command of God were to be <hi>deſtroyed,</hi> and even <hi>then</hi> too <hi>David</hi> acted under King <hi>Achiſh,</hi> as his chief Commiſſioner and General. 5. That from the beginning to the end of the whole matter, though <hi>David</hi> had ſo many Swords at his command, yet he never once Reſiſted his <hi>own</hi> Dread Soveraign, but only <hi>fled</hi> from him, and fled with more <hi>ſecurity</hi> than he could have done <hi>otherwiſe.</hi> Nay, tho <hi>David</hi> had <hi>to</hi> the <hi>faireſt</hi> opportunities, of making <hi>Saul</hi> his Priſoner, and of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away his Life, one in the Cave at <hi>Engedi,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. and another on the Hill of <hi>Hachilah,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26 yet ſtill he <hi>forbore</hi> all manner of <hi>violence,</hi> at both times uſing this Heroick and Loyal Expreſſion, <hi>The Lord forbid that I ſhould do this thing unto my Master the Lords Anointed, to ſtretch forth mine hand againſt him, ſeeing he is the Anointed of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whence I proceed to the next Concluſion, that the Deſtruction of the Lord's A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, the ſtretching forth the hand to Invade his Life or Dominions, is of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Acts of Violence, the moſt fearful and horrid Crime: <hi>The Lord forbid that I ſhould do this thing,</hi> ſaith <hi>David:</hi> When the Kingly Prophet <hi>David</hi> had privily cut off the skirt of <hi>Saul</hi>'s Robe (though it was only with a deſign to let him <hi>ſee</hi> that he had been in his Power) his Heart ſmote him, as if he had made a breach upon <hi>God's</hi> Law, and had been guilty of a very unworthy and Diſloyal Act (for the Oyl upon a Kings Head (like the Oyntment upon the Head of <hi>Aaron</hi> that deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon his skirts) makes even his Veſtments Sacred.) But with what Agonies and Convulſions would his Soul have been Tortured, had the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> been mocked by ſuch a <hi>Juncto</hi> of <hi>Jews,</hi> as Butcher'd the King of <hi>England,</hi> and in the name of the <hi>Lord</hi> vied for Wickedneſs with all the Devils in <hi>Hell?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſtory of <hi>Saul</hi>'s Death is a very ſad relation, all the <hi>parts</hi> and <hi>appurtenances</hi> thereof, together with <hi>Saul</hi>'s own Guilt, and the ſin of his Armour-bearer, and this <hi>Amalekite</hi> being rightly conſidered. But yet there are ſome paſſages in the ſtory, which it may not be amiſs for us to obſerve:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Concerning the Armour-bearer. <hi>Saul</hi> commanded him to draw his Sword, and to thruſt him through therewith, being deſirous rather to dye by the hands of his own Servant, than to be abuſed by the Uncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtines.</hi> But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Kings own Command, the Armour-bearer <hi>refuſed</hi> to hearken in that particular; <hi>he was ſore afraid,</hi> ſaith the Text, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 31.4. Read on now to the next v. and you will find, that this Armour-bearer feared not to Kill <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> though he was ſore <hi>afraid</hi> to Kill his Soveraign. By which inſtance it is clear, not only that he valued his <hi>Prince's</hi> Life far above his own, but alſo that he thought it much a more pardonable ſin to be a <hi>ſelf-Murderer,</hi> than to be a <hi>Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide,</hi> though tempted to be ſo by his Soveraigns Command. Doubtleſs, for a Man to Kill <hi>himſelf</hi> is a very horrid ſin, becauſe it is his laſt Act, whereby (in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152235:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:152235:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:152235:8"/>probability) he hurrieth himſelf off the Earth into Hell. Yet this Armour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer choſe rather to Dye with the Guilt of his own Blood upon his hands, than to Live Guilty of the Blood of the <hi>Lord's Anointed;</hi> and before he would be ſuch a Traitor, ran a ſad venture of being Damned for ever, by being <hi>Felo de ſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And then as for the <hi>Amalekite,</hi> that did effectually help on the Deſtruction of <hi>Saul,</hi> though he did it not of Malice, but upon <hi>Saul's</hi> intreaty; though he did it when <hi>Saul</hi> was now half breathleſs, and when he was ſure otherwiſe to be Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> though he did it to rid him of his preſent Fear and Pains, and ſtruck him more like a Friend, than an Enemy, doing no other than what <hi>Saul</hi> himſelf had already done in part; yet this <hi>Regicide's</hi> Conſcience ſeems to have been troubled preſently at an exceſſive rate: His breaſt was filled with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe, and Anguiſh, and Bitterneſs of Spirit, ſo that he could not but put on a mournful and penitential Habit; for he ran to <hi>David</hi> with his <hi>Clothes rent, and with Earth upon his Head,</hi> Confeſſing by his Actions, that he had committed an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Crime, when his Lying Tongue pretended that he had done a meritorious Act.</p>
            <p>Come thy ways now, my Honeſt <hi>Amalekite</hi> (Honeſt in Compariſon) who thô thou waſt not afraid to ſtretch forth thine hand to deſtroy the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ye for ought we know, didſt never ſuffer thine Heart to ſwell againſt thine own So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign; didſt never trample Faith and True Allegiance to thy Natural Prince; under thy Feet; didſt never break Covenants, nor violate Oaths, nor any ways further or abett the Blood-ſhedding of the King of <hi>Amalek;</hi> nor didſt ever har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den thy Heart to that deſperate ſtate of Impenitence, Deadneſs or Reprobation, as to Juſtifie and Vindicate the moſt horrid Act of Treaſon, with hands <hi>ſtretched out</hi> and <hi>lifted up before the moſt High God,</hi> as do thoſe Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> the Rebels of <hi>this</hi> day.</p>
            <p>And yet behold, a <hi>Greater</hi> Prince than either the King of <hi>Amalek</hi> or <hi>Saul,</hi> was here: Greater for his <hi>Lineage</hi> and <hi>Extraction;</hi> Greater for his Wiſdom, Faith, and <hi>Conſtancy</hi> to the <hi>Truth;</hi> Greater for all Vertues Divine, Moral, Political: Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er every ways, and only too Great by being too Good, for a moſt Unthankful and Improvident Nation.</p>
            <p>To draw now towards a concluſion, The deſign of this Diſcourſe is not ſo much to expoſe the Traytors, as to Repreſent the Sinfulneſs of the Treaſon, to the end we and our Poſterity may ſee what reaſon all of us have to be truly Humbled under the Senſe of it. For Rebellion is a Crying ſin, that filleth <hi>Heaven</hi> with its Noiſe and Clamour: And one reaſon of it is, becauſe it is not only an Injury againſt the <hi>Man,</hi> but moreover a Contumely, offered to the Majeſty of <hi>God,</hi> whoſe Image <hi>the Man</hi> bears; and therefore <hi>Philo</hi> the Jew calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Philo de Spec. Leg Sacriledge,</hi> and the Greateſt of all ſorts of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge:</hi> Nay, it is of ſuch a ſtaining nature, that it polluteth a whole Land; as God himſelf ſaid, <hi>Blood it defileth the Land, Num.</hi> 35.33. And an Inſtance hereof we have upon <hi>Saul</hi>'s killing the <hi>Gibeonites:</hi> He ſlew them indeed in his Zeal to the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah:</hi> but thô 'twas his Fact and Cruelty, yet a Three years Famine came upon the Land for it, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.1.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:152235:8"/>
            <p>And if all Innocent Blood eſpecially that of Rebellion ſtaineth a Nation ſo, how much more the ſhedding of Bloud <hi>Royal,</hi> the Bloud of <hi>Kings,</hi> who in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their High <hi>Office</hi> and Supreme <hi>Authority</hi> Repreſent God above all others, and bear his Image and Impreſs after a <hi>Peculiar</hi> and <hi>Eminent</hi> manner.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs, that I cannot but ſtill own my Fears, that our <hi>Land</hi> is not yet throughly cleanſed from the Bloud of that <hi>Innocent, Vertuous, Religious, Match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs</hi> Prince, who was barbarouſly murder'd among us. For though we may believe, that the merciful God will not require that Sacred Bloud of us, ſo as to make us ſmoak under that Wrath which is the vengeance of another life, (<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> eſpecially, who cannot read, nor ſo much as <hi>Think</hi> of that Diſmal Tragedy without the deepeſt <hi>Sorrow Hatred,</hi> and <hi>Abomination</hi>) yet we have too great Reaſon to ſuſpect that the Sin is not forgotten in <hi>Heaven,</hi> that there is no ſuch <hi>Act of Oblivien There,</hi> but that as we have Smarted for that Sin <hi>already,</hi> ſo we may Smart ſtill under thoſe Plagues and Judgments which are the Diſcipline of this life. We are to diſtinguiſh between a <hi>Sin</hi> and its <hi>Puniſhment.</hi> The <hi>Sin</hi> may be <hi>forgiven,</hi> and upon true Repentance is certainly forgiven, ſo that it ſhall not Riſe up in Judgment againſt the Sinner at the <hi>last</hi> day: But ſeldom does the Cry of a <hi>Vocal</hi> Sin <hi>ceaſe,</hi> before God letteth loſe ſome <hi>Temporal</hi> Judgments upon it; either for the <hi>warning</hi> and <hi>Admonition</hi> of <hi>other Men,</hi> or for the <hi>Correction</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> of the Sinners <hi>themſelves</hi> or for the exerciſing of their <hi>Patience,</hi> or for the like <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly</hi> and <hi>Gracious</hi> purpoſes. The <hi>thing</hi> is clear from that Inſtance con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>David,</hi> whom God viſited with the Death of his Child, and with ſharp and poynant Evils for the Wickedneſs acted upon <hi>Bathſheba</hi> and her Husband, though the Sin it <hi>ſelf</hi> was forgiven him. <hi>The Lord hath put away thy Sin, thou ſhalt not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> ſaid Nathan; <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wbeit, becauſe by this Deed thou haſt given great Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to the Enemies of the Lord to Blaſpheme, the Child that is born unto thee ſhall ſurely die,</hi> 2 Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2.</p>
            <p>Nor is it a juſt Ground for our <hi>Confidence</hi> and <hi>Security</hi> to conſider, that that Sin was acted by a Few in compariſon) and that ſeveral Years ago too.</p>
            <p>For, the Sin of <hi>One</hi> Man (and much rather of an <hi>Army</hi>) may be ſo Odious and Abominable in God's Account, that by <hi>Occaſion</hi> thereof he may viſit the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquities of a whole Nation, let us go to <hi>Achan</hi> for an Inſtance: Upon the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>Jericho, Achan</hi> found a <hi>Babylon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh Garment, a wedg of Gold, and two Hundred Sheckles of Silver; and becauſe he took of the Accurſed thing,</hi> the <hi>Anger</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> was kindled againſt the whole Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo that at the very next Battle, they were all <hi>routed</hi> by their Enemies, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Again,</hi> God is not wont to puniſh a Nation to the <hi>Full,</hi> as ſoon as the Sin is <hi>committed,</hi> but uſually <hi>leaves</hi> a great part of the Burden, many <hi>Talents</hi> of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to fall down in <hi>after-times,</hi> to put Men ſtill in mind of that Guilt, which otherwiſe they would bury in perpetual <hi>Oblivion.</hi> Let us go for an Inſtance hereof to the <hi>Jews</hi> in the days of <hi>Moſes. At Shittim</hi> they joyn themſelves to <hi>Baal-Peor,</hi> and a Plague enſueth thereupon. But, though for <hi>Phinehas</hi> his <hi>zeal,</hi> the Plague was ſoon ſtayed, and the VVrath of God was turned away from <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> for that time, yet afterwards in the days of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152235:9"/>been Poſſeſſed of the Holy Land, <hi>Phineas</hi> himſelf remembred the Iniquity of <hi>Peor,</hi> and told the People that <hi>they were not cleanſed from that Iniquity unto that day,</hi> Joſh. 22.17.</p>
            <p>Now (to draw down this Conſideration to our <hi>ſelves</hi>) if God be wont by way of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> to chaſtiſe Evil Men, even after they have taken away the Guilt of their Wickedneſs; if by occaſion of <hi>One</hi> crying Sin, committed by a <hi>Few,</hi> or perhaps by <hi>One</hi> only, he doth ſometimes bring Calamities upon a whole <hi>Nation;</hi> and if this be often done ſome conſiderable <hi>time,</hi> ſome <hi>years after</hi> the Sin was acted: Then truly, we of all People living have moſt reaſon to call to mind the Calamities we have groaned under, and to Interpret Providence the <hi>Right</hi> way, and not only to <hi>miſtruſt</hi> that God hath viſited us, hitherto, but moreover to <hi>fear</hi> that he will viſit us ſtill (eſpecially, if we repent not from the bottom of our Hearts) for that <hi>loud and clamorous</hi> Rebellion which brought the Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Lords Anointed</hi> (and a Man according to Gods own Heart too) though he was deſtroyed and murder'd, not by our <hi>own</hi> Hands, but by the Hands of <hi>Amalekites,</hi> and that ſo long ſince.</p>
            <p>Now, what if we ſhould conceive, that <hi>when this City</hi> was turned into a Flaming pile, the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God came to purge it from the Bloud of his <hi>Anointed?</hi> When the <hi>Jews</hi> of old were in any ſharp afflictions, the buſineſs of the <hi>Golden Calf</hi> uſually came freſh into their minds, and on every turn they miſtruſted, that God afflicted them from the Iniquity of their Fathers in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a <hi>Golden Calf.</hi> The ſtory of it you have at large in <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. the People would have ſome Repreſentation to go before them <hi>inſtead</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> their proper <hi>Captain</hi> and <hi>Leader;</hi> they prevailed with <hi>Aaron</hi> to <hi>conſent</hi> and <hi>concur</hi> with them, and they contributed their <hi>Riches,</hi> their <hi>Gold</hi> and their <hi>Ear-rings</hi> to carry on the Work of the day; and at laſt out came a <hi>Calf,</hi> a little <hi>Similitude</hi> of the Great <hi>Idol,</hi> which was Worſhipped in the Houſe of Bondage, whence they had now been delivered, ſo that, though they had eſcaped out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> yet they eſpouſed the <hi>Egyptian Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And why ſhould we not think now, that when God viſited us with his Judgments, he did not remember Peoples Ingratitude to him and his Anointed? Or why ſhould we not fear that he will remember us again and that with more Sore and more Dreadful Judgments, if People perſiſt in their Ingratitude ſtill? For this is a Sin of no ordinary rate, but one of the Firſt Magnitude; the King's Authority being a Donative of Heaven, and a Ray of God's Majeſty, and his Power to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern and Puniſh, being given by God's own Warrantry, the Sin of Rebellion muſt neceſſarily be of a Damning Nature, and of a Clamorous Tongue, however ſome (whoſe Conſciences are Armour proof againſt all Arguments from Scripture and Antiquity) have begun again to ſpeak of the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſ; of Reſiſtance, as if their hands were already laid upon the Hilts of their Swords.</p>
            <p>Take heed therefore (<hi>you</hi> eſpecially of this <hi>Great City</hi>) that ye join not in the Confederacies of <hi>Korah,</hi> leaſt ye utterly <hi>Periſh</hi> in his gain ſaying. <hi>Is the Iniquity of Peor,</hi> and the Sin of the <hi>Golden Calf</hi> to little for us? Are not the Judgments, which we have groaned under, heavy enough <hi>yet,</hi> but do we ſollicite God to add <hi>more</hi> Talents to the weight <hi>ſtill?</hi> Aſſure your ſelves, that if People Repeat their Rebellious <hi>Sins,</hi> God will not fail to Repeat and Double his <hi>Blows;</hi> and he hath more Judgments in Treaſure beſides the <hi>Plague</hi> and the <hi>Fire;</hi> and the <hi>Poſterity</hi> that cometh after us will (as we our ſelves have done) ſee the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ollies, and ſmart greatly for the Impieties of their Fathers; for as <hi>Ezra</hi> ſaid upon the Return out of Captivity, <hi>After all that is come upon us for our Evil deeds, and for our Great treſpaſs, ſeeing that God hath puniſhed us leſs than our iniquities deſerve, and hath given us a Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance</hi> (a miraculous deliverance out of our Thraldom) <hi>ſhould we again break his Commandments, and join with the People in theſe Rebellions, would not God be Angry with us till he had Conſumed us, ſo that there ſhould be no Remnant, nor Eſcaping?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the preventing of the <hi>worſt</hi> of Evils it is our great <hi>Concernment,</hi> and ought to be our great <hi>Care,</hi> and 'twill be found to be our beſt Intereſt, when all is done, to lay aſide all Unnatural Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities and Heart-burnings, which Evil Men have ſo long made uſe of, In order to diſtract this Kingdom; and to be filled with the true and primitive Spirit of Chriſtianity; to be Meek, and Gentle, and of Humble Minds; to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct according to that Wiſdom, which is <hi>Pure</hi> and <hi>Peaceable;</hi> to Study to be Quiet; to endeavour by all poſſible means <hi>to keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace;</hi> to be Tractable and Honeſt in Heart; to be ſubject to the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> and that not for fear of the <hi>Laws</hi> only, but readily and ingenuouſly, and for <hi>Conſcience-ſake, to Fear God, to Honour the King, and to Love the Brother-hood;</hi> to be in perfect <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> among our ſelves, as <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh</hi> Brethren; and ſo, in all manner of <hi>well-doing</hi> to commit our ſelves to <hi>God;</hi> to whom be <hi>Glory, Dominion</hi> and <hi>Praiſe.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer/>
            <postscript>
               <p>This Diſcourſe ought to have been inſiſted on by the Doctor, rather than that ſeditious Sermon that he preach't at <hi>Exon.</hi>
               </p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <p>With Allowance.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152235:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
